<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">

<document>
<header>
  <title>The Grinder, a Java Load Testing Framework</title>
</header>
  <body>

    <section>
    <title>What is The Grinder?</title>

    <p>The Grinder is a Java<sup>TM</sup> load-testing framework. It
    is freely available under a BSD-style open-source <a
    href="site:license">license</a>.</p>

    <p>The Grinder makes it easy to orchestrate the activities of a
    test script in many processes across many machines, using a
    graphical console application. Test scripts make use of client
    code embodied in Java <em>plug-ins</em>. Most users of The Grinder
    do not write plug-ins themselves, instead they use one of the
    supplied plug-ins. The Grinder comes with a mature plug-in for
    testing HTTP services, as well as a tool which allows HTTP scripts
    to be automatically recorded.</p>

    <p>The Grinder was originally developed for the book
    <em>Professional Java 2 Enterprise Edition with BEA WebLogic
    Server</em> by Paco G&#xf3;mez and Peter Zadrozny. Philip Aston
    took ownership of the code and reworked it to create <strong>The
    Grinder 2</strong>. Philip continues to enhance and maintain The
    Grinder, and welcomes all contributions. Recently Peter, Philip
    and Ted Osborne have published the book <a
    href="site:links/book">J2EE Performance Testing</a> which makes
    extensive use of The Grinder.</p>

    <p>The next major version of The Grinder, <a
    href="site:g3/whats-new">The Grinder 3</a> is currently available
    as a beta quality release. The Grinder 3 uses the powerful
    scripting language Jython, and allows any Java code to be tested
    without the need to write a plug-in.</p>

    <p>The latest news, downloads, and mailing list archives can be
    found on <a href="ext:sourceforge/grinder">SourceForge.net</a>.
    </p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Authors</title>
      <table class="noborder">
  <tr><td>Paco Gómez</td></tr>
  <tr><td>Philip Aston</td></tr>
  <tr><td>Phil Dawes</td></tr>
  <tr><td>Paddy Spencer</td></tr>
  <tr><td>Richard Wallace</td></tr>
  <tr><td>Stuart Tily</td></tr>
  <tr><td>Phillip Burgess</td></tr>
  <tr><td>Christian Nedregard</td></tr>
  <tr><td>Mikael Suokas</td></tr>
  <tr><td>David Freels</td></tr>
  <tr><td>Kalle Burbeck</td></tr>
  <tr><td>Dirk Feufel</td></tr>
  <tr><td>Kjetil JD</td></tr>
  <tr><td>Todd Wasson</td></tr>
  <tr><td>Jose Antonio Zapata Rey</td></tr>
  <tr><td>Richard Perks</td></tr>
  <tr><td>Manuel Silva</td></tr>
  <tr><td>Bill Schnellinger</td></tr>
  <tr><td>Bertrand Ave</td></tr>
  <tr><td>Huibert Alblas</td></tr>
  <tr><td>Kalyanaraman Venkatasubramaniy</td></tr>
  <tr><td>John Stanford White</td></tr>
  <tr><td>Slavik Gnatenko</td></tr>
  <tr><td>Marc Born</td></tr>
  <tr><td>Andreas Schmidt</td></tr>
  <tr><td>Calum Fitzgerald</td></tr>
  <tr><td>Sebastián Fontana</td></tr>
  <tr><td>KArol Muszynski</td></tr>
  <tr><td>Meo Bogliolo</td></tr>
  <tr><td>Konstantin Ignatyev</td></tr>
  <tr><td>Martin Wagner</td></tr>
      </table>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Credits</title>

      <p>I wish to thank Paco Gómez and Peter Zadrozny for the
      key ideas embodied in the original version of The Grinder.</p>

      <p>I am grateful to VA Software for SourceForge.net.</p>

      <p>This site was put together with <code>txt2html</code>, <a
      href="ext:xemacs" class="external">XEmacs</a> and <a
      href="ext:forrest">Apache Forrest</a>.</p>

      <p><strong>Philip Aston</strong></p>
   </section>
</body>
</document>
