<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">

<document>
<header>
  <title>External references</title>
</header>

<body>
<section>
  <title>Articles</title>

  <table class="noborder">
    <tr>
      <td>
        <a
        href="http://www.gashalot.com/blog/archives/000002.html">Gash:
        Load Testing Java Applications</a>
      </td>
      <td>Replacing JMeter with The Grinder 3

       <p class="quote">"I went from a freshly downloaded tarball to
       fully functional test environment in about 2.5 hours. That's
       powerful."</p>
      </td>
    </tr>

    <tr>
      <td>
        <a href="http://c2.com/cgi/wiki/wiki?TheGrinder">WikiWikiWeb</a>
      </td>

      <td>Entry on the Wiki of Wiki's.</td>
    </tr>

    <tr>
      <td>
        <a href="http://mapage.noos.fr/kimble/papers/grinder.htm">Stress Testing with The Grinder and Cactus</a>
      </td>

      <td>Using The Grinder 2's JUnit plug-in with Cactus.</td>
    </tr>

    <tr>
      <td>
        <a href="http://dev2dev.bea.com/articles/aston.jsp">The Grinder: Load Testing for Everyone</a>
      </td>

      <td>An introductory article on The Grinder 2 from Phil Aston.</td>
    </tr>

    <tr>
      <td>
        <a href="http://www.massivepropeller.com/users/austin/blogs/whatsnew/archive/000043.html">Massive Propeller: The Grinder</a>
      </td>

      <td>Blog entry on The Grinder 2.</td>
    </tr>

    <tr>
      <td>
        <a href="http://http://213.243.170.17/MrWorm/35">Mr Worm's GonePage: The Grinder</a>
      </td>

      <td>Blog entry on The Grinder.</td>
    </tr>

    <tr>
      <td>
        <a href="http://www.mooreds.com/weblog/archives/000111.html">Dan Moore!: The Grinder</a>
      </td>

      <td>Blog entry on The Grinder 3.</td>
    </tr>
  </table>
</section>

<section>
  <title>Commercials</title>

  <p>This section contains links to commercial products and services
  related to The Grinder. You should not assume any relationship other
  than those documented below between the listed individuals and
  companies and The Grinder project.

  If you have a product or service related to The Grinder and would
  like to add information to this page, please email details to <a
  href="ext:mail/grinder-use">grinder-use</a>.</p>

  <section id="book">
    <title>J2EE Performance Testing</title>

    <p>I'm pleased to announce the availability of <em><a
    href="ext:j2ee-performance-testing">J2EE Performance Testing with
    BEA WebLogic Server</a></em> by Peter Zadrozny, Philip Aston and
    Ted Osborne, originally published by Expert Press and now by
    APress.</p>

    <figure src="images/book-cover.jpg" alt="The Book"/>

    <p>This book uses The Grinder 2 throughout, and indeed was
    responsible for driving the development of many of The Grinder's
    features. The book shows how to performance test complete J2EE
    applications and how to explore key performance issues surrounding
    the most popular J2EE APIs. The performance tests are carried out
    using BEA WebLogic Server&#8482;, but are generally applicable to
    any J2EE application server.</p>

    <p>Most importantly, the book contains in-depth coverage of The
    Grinder 2 including a full user guide and case studies showing how
    to apply The Grinder to real world problems. The testing approach
    is equally applicable when using The Grinder 3.</p>

    <p>Following several requests, I've made the source code for the
    book available from <a href="ext:sourceforge/grinder">The Grinder
    SourceForge page</a>. This source is supplied unsupported and with
    no warranty.</p>

    <p>Philip Aston</p>

  </section>

  <section id="testpros">
    <title>TestPros</title>

    <p>TestPros provides load testing and performance tuning services
    using Grinder. We can provide our services in one or a combination
    of three ways - remotely via our Internet server farm, at our test
    labs, or at our customer's location.</p>

    <p>For more information:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>1-877-783-7855</li>
      <li><a href="ext:testpros/mail">info@TestPros.com</a></li>
      <li><a href="ext:testpros">www.TestPros.com</a></li>
    </ul>
  </section>

  <section id="swtest-discuss">
    <title>swtest-discuss</title>

    <p>I run a mailing list for software testers called <a
    href="ext:swtest-discuss">swtest-discuss</a>. There are a few
    people there (including me) who are interested in talking about
    how people do testing for open source projects. I haven't yet
    found a community of open source testers that cuts across multiple
    tools/applications.</p>

    <p>If you're interested in sharing your experiences in testing
    open source software, please consider joining swtest-discuss, at
    least long enough to see if there's any interest in having an
    on-going forum on this topic. If you do subscribe, please either
    send me a private email or introduce yourself to the list so we
    know you're there.</p>

    <p>Danny R. Faught, <a href="ext:tejasconsulting">Tejas Software
    Consulting</a></p>
  </section>

</section>
</body>
</document>
