<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">

<document>
<header>
  <title>Jython</title>
</header>
<body>


  <section>
    <title>Scripts</title>

    <p>The requirements for Jython scripts can be found in the <a
    href="site:scripts-intro/jython-scripts/">introduction</a>. </p>

  </section>

  <section id="jython-installation">
    <title>The Jython distribution and installation</title>

    <p>The Grinder is shipped with a version of Jython but does not
    package the Jython implementation of the standard Python library. If
    you want to use the standard library, or if you want to use a
    different version of Jython, you should first obtain and install
    Jython.</p>

    <section>
    <title>Traditional Jython installation</title>


    <p>If you use its standard options, the Jython installer will
    create a new directory containing the Jython jar file, the library
    modules, examples, and documentation. You need to tell The Grinder
    the location of this directory. You can do this either by adding
    the following to your <a href="site:properties">properties</a>
    file:</p>

    <source class="sh">
grinder.jvm.arguments = -Dpython.home=/opt/jython/jython2.2.1
    </source>

    <p>or on the agent command line:</p>

    <source class="sh">
java -Dgrinder.jvm.arguments=-Dpython.home=/opt/jython/jython2.2.1 net.grinder.Grinder
    </source>

    <p>In both cases, change <code>/opt/jython/jython2.2.1</code> to the
    directory in which you installed Jython. You must install Jython on all
    of the agent machines. If the version of Jython is different to that
    included with The Grinder (2.2.1), you should also add the
    installation's <code>jython.jar</code>  to the start of the
    <code>CLASSPATH</code> used to launch the agent.</p>

    <note>
    Adding the installation's <code>jython.jar</code>
    to the start of the <code>CLASSPATH</code> used to be sufficient for
    Jython to calculate its install directory, but this no longer appears
    to work with Jython 2.2.1. You must explicitly set <code>python.home</code>
    as described above.
    </note>

    <p>Jython picks up user and site preferences from several sources
    (see <a
    href="ext:jython/registry">http://www.jython.org/docs/registry.html</a>).
    A side effect of setting <code>python.home</code> is that the
    installed registry file will be used.</p>
    </section>

    <section id="jython-standalone-jar">
    <title>Simpler installation using Jython's standalone jar</title>

    <p>Newer versions of Jython have a <em>standalone</em>
    installation mode. The Jython installer can be used to create a
    <code>jython.jar</code> file that includes the standard library.</p>

    <p>
    You can generate a standalone <code>jython.jar</code> and use it
    to replace the file in The Grinder's <code>lib</code> directory.
    This is simple, and does not require you to set
    <code>python.home</code>.</p>

    </section>

    <section id="jython-cachedir">
    <title>Setting the Jython cache directory</title>

    <p>Another feature that is not working in later versions of Jython is the
    correct calculation of the cache directory. If you don't have a Jython
    cache directory, wild card imports of Java packages (e.g.
    <code> from java.util import *</code>) may not work, The Grinder will
    take a little longer to start, and ugly error messages will be displayed:
    </p>

    <source class="text">
28/09/08 17:57:11 (agent): worker paston01-0 started
*sys-package-mgr*: can't create package cache dir, '/home/performance/lib/jython.jar/cachedir/packages'
    </source>

    <p>You can specify the cache directory either by setting the
    <code>python.home</code> as above (in which case the directory will
    that specified in the Python registry), or by setting the Java property
    <code>python.cachedir</code> in your <a href="site:properties">properties</a> file:
    </p>

    <source class="sh">
grinder.jvm.arguments = -Dpython.cachedir=/tmp/mycache
    </source>

    <p>or on the command line:</p>

    <source class="sh">
java -Dgrinder.jvm.arguments = -Dpython.cachedir=/tmp/mycache net.grinder.Grinder
    </source>

    <p>You can only set <code>grinder.jvm.arguments</code> once, so
    if you want to set both the cache directory and <code>python.home</code>
    either use the registry, or do this:</p>

    <source class="sh">
grinder.jvm.arguments = -Dpython.home=/opt/jython/jython2.2.1 -Dpython.cachedir=/tmp/mycache
    </source>

    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="jython-2.5">
    <title>Jython 2.5</title>

  <p>The default Jython implementation packaged with The Grinder is
  Jython 2.2. The Grinder 3.3 and later optionally support Jython 2.5,
  as described on this page. Jython 2.5.1 has also been tested and
  works fine.</p>

  <p>Jython 2.5.2 works with The Grinder 3.5 or later.</p>

  <section>
    <title>How to use Jython 2.5</title>

    <p>Download and install Jython 2.5. Add the path to the installation's jython.jar
    file to the start of the <code>CLASSPATH</code> you use for The Grinder agent processes.
    If you wish to use the library modules, you should also
    <a href="site:jython-installation">set the python.home</a> property to
    point to the installation directory.</p>

    <p>The support for Jython 2.5 uses the
    <a href="site:new-instrumentation">new instrumentation engine</a>,
  and requires that the agent processes are run using Java SE 6.</p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Known issues</title>

    <p>You may find the need to remove or rename the <code>jython.jar</code>
      file from the <code>lib</code> directory.
      See this <a href="site:sre-assertion">FAQ</a>.</p>

    <p>The Grinder 3.5 improved the instrumentation of Java methods
    from Jython. If you are using an earlier version of The Grinder,
    instrumentation of Java methods may not work as you expect. See <a
    href="site:sourceforge/bug2992248">bug 2992248</a>.
    </p>

  </section>

  </section>

</body>
</document>
