<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">

<document>
<header>
  <title>What's new in The Grinder 3?</title>
</header>

<body>
  <p>This section summarises the changes between The Grinder 2 and The
  Grinder 3. If you're not familiar with The Grinder 2, skim read this
  and move on to <a href="site:getting-started">Getting
  Started</a>.</p>

  <section>
    <title>Jython</title>

    <p><icon src="images/PythonPoweredSmall.gif" alt="Python
    powered"/> The most significant change that The Grinder 3
    introduces is a <a href="ext:jython">Jython</a> (the Java
    implementation of Python) scripting engine that is used to execute
    test scripts. Test scripts replace the specification of tests in
    the <code>grinder.properties</code> file. The
    <code>grinder.properties</code> file is still used to specify
    general control information (how to contact the console, how many
    worker processes to use, ..), as well as the name of the test
    script. Many other key features of The Grinder 2, such as the
    console and the process architecture, remain unchanged.</p>

    <p>The scripting engine provides the following new
    capabilities:</p>

    <dl>
      <dt><strong>Test any Java code</strong></dt>

      <dd><p>The Grinder 3 allows any Java (or Jython) code to be
      encapsulated as a test. This practically removes the need to
      write custom plug-ins. Although plug-ins are no longer
      responsible for performing tests, they can still be useful to
      manage objects that the tests use. For example, the HTTP plug-in
      manages a pool of connections for each worker thread, and
      provides an <code>HTTPRequest</code> object that makes use of
      these connections.</p></dd>

      <dt><strong>Dynamic test scripting</strong></dt>

      <dd>
        <p>The Grinder 2 worker processes execute tests in the
        properties file sequentially in a fixed order, and there is
        limited support in some of the The Grinder 2 plug-ins for
        checking test results. The Grinder 3 allows arbitrary
        branching and looping and makes test results directly
        available to the test script, allowing different test paths to
        be taken depending on the outcome of each test.</p>

        <p>The Grinder 2 HTTP plug-in's <a
        href="site:g2/http-plugin/string-bean">string bean</a> feature
        provides simple support for requests that contain dynamic
        data. The Grinder 3 can use the full power of Jython to create
        dynamic requests of arbitrary complexity.</p>
      </dd>
    </dl>

    <p>Kind of dry, huh? If you never seen any Python or are wondering
    what was wrong with the old <code>grinder.properties</code>
    approach then skip ahead to the <a
    href="site:script-gallery">Script Gallery</a> where you can
    sample the power of The Grinder 3.</p>

  </section>

  <section>
    <title>New distribution packaging</title>

    <p>The Grinder is distributed in separate binary and source
    <code>zip</code> files. They can be downloaded from <a
    href="ext:sourceforge/grinder">SourceForge.net</a>.</p>

    <p>To simplify SSL and HTTPS configuration, JSSE is now
    <em>required</em> for The Grinder 3. Consequently you may find it
    easier to use J2SE 1.4.1 with The Grinder 3.</p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Other changes</title>

    <ul>
      <li>The TCPSniffer has been renamed <em>TCPProxy</em> for
      correctness. The TCPProxy can be used with other HTTP and HTTPS
      proxies.</li>

      <li>Console signals are now transmitted over a TCP socket
      connection. Mulicast is no longer used.</li>

      <li>The interface that plug-ins must implement has changed
      significantly. Plug-ins written for The Grinder 2 will not work
      with The Grinder 3.</li>

      <li>Many <a
      href="site:getting-started/properties"><code>grinder.properties</code></a>
      have been removed. The features formerly accessed through
      setting properties are now set by making calls to the plug-in
      from the test script. Some of the remaining property names have
      been renamed.</li>

      <li>HTTP tests can now be directed through an HTTP proxy.</li>

      <li>String beans and OK strings have been removed from the HTTP
      plug-in. String beans and OK strings are very limited in
      comparison to to the flexibility now provided by Jython
      scripts.</li>

      <li>The <code>HttpURLConnection</code> implementation has been
      removed from the HTTP plug-in.</li>

      <li>The JUnit and Socket plug-ins have been removed. Their
      functionality can be achieved directly by using the appropriate
      Java objects in scripts.</li>
    </ul>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Roadmap</title>

    <p>This section documents things that are planned for The Grinder
    3. There are no current release dates for these features.</p>

    <section>
      <title>Test script distribution</title>

      <p>From the Grinder 3 console you will be able to edit test
      scripts and then distribute them to the worker processes. It
      will no longer be necessary to copy grinder.properties files
      around or to use a shared disk.</p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Embedded Agent</title>

      <p>A new agent will be provided that can be loaded within an
      existing Java Virtual Machine. This will allow, for example,
      threads to be started within an application server which can run
      test scripts that make direct calls against local resources such
      as EJBs.</p>
    </section>
  </section>

</body>
</document>
