<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<html>
<body>

<h1>Internationalisation help wanted</h1>

<p>If you are bilingual you might fancy translating the console into a
language of your choice. Jose Antonio Zapta Rey did just this and
produced a Spanish translation.</p>

<blockquote>
<img src="../images/console-es-g3.png" width="720" height="480"/>
</blockquote>

<p> This translation will be automaically be the default for users
with their locale set correctly for the Spanish language. If your
locale is set otherwise and you are curious to try this out, specify
the Java <code>user.langauge</code> system property.</p>

<blockquote>
<pre>
java -Duser.language="es" net.grinder.Console
</pre>
</blockquote>

<p>Bertrand Ave has produced a translation for French speaking users
(<code>user.language="fr"</code>) and Alblas Huibert has produced a
German translation (<code>user.language="de"</code>).</p>

<h2>How to provide a translation</h2>

<p>Download and expand the latest source distribution of The Grinder.
Look in the <code>src/net/grinder/console/swingui/resources</code>
directory. The definition of all English text used by the console is
contained in the <code>Console.properties</code> file. Individual
translations are contained in <code>Console_XX.properties</code> where
XX is the two letter <a
href="http://ftp.ics.uci.edu/pub/ietf/http/related/iso639.txt">ISO 639
language code</a>. For example, the Spanish translation is contained
in <code>Console_es.properties</code>.</p>

<p>Use a text editor to create a translated file for your language of
choice. The existing translations will guide you as to which
properties you need to translate. You should only include properties
that have translated text. Don't include properties such as
<code>scriptTab.image</code> that refer to images, or properties that
refer to logical names such as <code>action.menu</code>.</p>

<p>To test your file before contributing it, place the file in a
directory structure matching
<code>src/net/grinder/console/swingui/resources</code> and add the
directory that contains <code>src</code> to the start of the
<code>CLASSPATH</code> that you use to start the console. You may need
to set <code>user.language</code> as described above.</p>

<p>Post your translation to <a
href="mailto:grinder-development@lists.sourceforge.net">grinder-development
list</a>. Please also include a statement that you are happy for your
work to be distributed under the terms of <a
href="../license.html">The Grinder license</a>.</p>

</body>
</html>
