<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<html>
<body>

<image src="../images/script-logo.png"/>

<h1>What's new in The Grinder 3?</h1>

<p>The key change introduced by The Grinder 3 is a full scripting
engine to define test scripts. This replaces the specification of
tests in the <code>grinder.properties</code> file. Most of the other
key features of The Grinder 2, such as the console and the process
architecture, are unchanged.</p>

<h2>Jython</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.jython.org">Jython</a> is the Java
implementation of the Python scripting language. A Jython engine has
been introduced into The Grinder to address the following.</p>

<blockquote>
<h4>Dynamic test scripting</h4>

<p>The Grinder 2 is limited in that each worker process executes the
tests in the test script sequentially, in a fixed order. The Grinder 3
uses Jython scripts to allow arbitrary branching and looping.</p>

<p>There is very limited support in some of the The Grinder 2 plug-ins
for checking the results of tests. The Grinder 3 makes these results
directly available to the test script, allowing various test paths to
be taken depending on the responses returned by the server.</p>

<h4>Dynamic data</h4>

<p>The Grinder 2 HTTP plug-in's <a
href="../manual/http-plugin.html#string-bean">string bean</a> feature
provides simple support for requests that contain dynamic data. The
Grinder 3 can use the full power of Jython to create dynamic requests
of arbitrary complexity.</p>

</blockquote>

<p>Kind of dry, huh? If you never seen any Python or are wondering
what was wrong with the old <code>grinder.properties</code> approach
then skip ahead the <a href="./script-galley.html">Script Gallery</a>
to sample the power of The Grinder 3.</p>

<h2>New Java plug-in</h2>

<p>A powerful new "Java" plug-in has been introduced which allows
arbitrary Java and Jython code to be tested. This practically removes
the need to write custom plug-ins.</p>

<h2>Support for multiple plug-ins</h2>

<p>A single script can use multiple plug-ins.</p>

<h2>New plug-in SPI</h2>

<p>The interface that plug-ins must implement has changed
significantly. Plug-ins written for The Grinder 2 will not work with
The Grinder 3 without significant modification.</p>

<h2>New distribution packaging</h2>

<p>The Grinder is distributed in separate binary and source
<code>zip</code> files.</p>

<h2>Other changes</h2>

<ul>
<li>The HTTP plug-in can now be used through an HTTP proxy.</li>
<li>Many <a
href="./properties.html"><code>grinder.properties</code></a> have been
removed. The features formally set through properties are now set by
making calls to the plug-in from the test script. Some of the
remaining property names have been renamed.</li>
</ul>

<h1>What's gone?</h1>

<h2>The JUnit and Socket plug-ins</h2>

<p>The JUnit and Socket plug-ins have been removed. There
functionality can be achieved with the new, more general, Java
plug-in.</p>

<h2>HTTP plug-in features</h2>

<p>String beans and OK strings have been removed from the HTTP
plug-in. String beans and OK strings are very limited in comparison to
to the flexibility now provided by the Jython scripting engine.</p>

<p>The <code>HttpURLConnection</code> implementation has been
removed.</p>

</body>
</html>
