<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<html>
<body>

<h1>What's new in The Grinder 3?</h1>

<p><em>The key change that The Grinder 3 introduces is a full
scripting engine to define test scripts. This replaces the
specification of tests in the <code>grinder.properties</code> file.
Most of the other key features of The Grinder 2 are unchanged (the
console, the process architecture).</em></p>

<img src="../images/PythonPoweredSmall.gif" alt="Python Powered"
align="right"/>

<h2>Jython</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.jython.org">Jython</a> is the Java
implementation of the Python scripting language. A Jython engine has
been introduced into The Grinder to address the following.</p>

<blockquote>
<h4>Dynamic test scheduling</h4>

<p>The Grinder 2 is limited in that each worker process executes the
tests in the test script sequentially, in a fixed order. The Grinder 3
uses Jython scripts to allow arbitrary branching and looping.</p>

<h4>Dynamic data</h4>

<p>The Grinder 2 HTTP plug-in's <a
href="../manual/http-plugin.html#string-bean">string bean</a> feature
provides simple support for requests that contain dynamic data. The
Grinder 3 can use the full power of Jython to create dynamic requests
of arbitrary complexity.</p>

<h4>Checking responses</h4>

<p>There is very limited support in some of the The Grinder 2 plug-ins
for checking the results of tests. The Grinder 3 makes these results
directly available to the test script, allowing various test paths to
be taken depending on the responses returned by the server.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Kind of dry, huh? If you never seen any Python or are wondering
what was wrong with the old <code>grinder.properties</code> approach
then skip ahead the <a href="./script-galley">Script Gallery</a> to
sample the power of G3.</p>

<h2>New Java plug-in</h2>

<p>A powerful new "Java" plug-in has been introduced which allows
arbitrary Java and Jython code to be tested.</p>

<h2>Support for multiple plug-ins</h2>

<p>A single script can use multiple plug-ins.</p>

<h2>New distribution packaging</h2>

<p>The Grinder is distributed in separate binary and source
<code>zip</code> files.</p>

<h1>What's gone?</h1>

</body>
</html>
